A Finding Aid to the Merry Renk Papers, 1952-2000, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Merry Renk papers
1952-2000
Archives of American Art
Renk, Merry, 1921-2012
AAA.renkmerr
Archival Resource Key
0.9 Linear feet
The papers of San Francisco metal-worker, jeweler, and painter Merry Renk measure 0.9 linear feet and date from 1952 to 2000. The collection comprises business records that include sales invoices, inventories, exhibition price lists, correspondence, and other material related to Renk's business activities. Also found are printed materials, a few sketches of utensils, writings, and a video recording of the documentary "Merry Renk: Jeweler" by Alan Leveton.
Biographical / Historical
Merry Renk (1921-2012) was a jeweler, painter, and metal-worker in San Francisco, California.
Renk was born in Trenton, New Jersey as Mary Ruth Gibbs. She studied painting at the Trenton School of Industrial Arts before moving to Chicago in 1946 to study at Illinois Institute of Technology. In Chicago, Renk founded the 750 Studio, an art gallery, with Olive Oliver and Mary Jo Slick. After taking some time to travel, she settled in San Francisco in 1948 where she became a prominent member of the arts and crafts community. Renk was instrumental in the founding of the San Francisco Metal Arts Guild and served as president in 1954. She also became an honorary fellow at the American Craft Council.
Renk is primarily known for her jewelry work but after suffering an eye injury in a car accident she began focusing on creating large scale sculptures using jewelry techniques sometime in the 1960s to 1970s.
Renk married Stanley Edwin Renk in 1941. After his death in World War II, she married fellow artist Earle Watt Curtis in 1958.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection, the papers are arranged as one series.
Series 1: Merry Renk Papers, 1952-2000 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, OV 3)
Scope and Contents
The papers of San Francisco jeweler, painter, and metal-worker Merry Renk measure 0.9 linear feet and date from 1952 to 2000. The collection comprises business records that include sales invoices, inventories, exhibition price lists, and correspondence. Correspondents include Greta Daniel, Mrs. Vanderbilt Webb, Conrad Brown, Rose Slivka, Paul Soldner, Paul J. Smith, Alice W. Nichols, Roger Armstrong, and Francis S. Merritt. Also found is other material related to Renk's business activities; printed materials including clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs; a few sketches of utensils; writings including an unpublished typescript with illustrations and a draft of Renk's biographical statement; and a video recording containing the documentary "Merry Renk: Jeweler" by Alan Leveton.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Merry Renk papers were donated in 2003 and 2004 by Merry Renk as a part of the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Related Materials
Also in the Archives of American Art is an interview of Merry Renk conducted on January 18-19, 2001 by Arline M. Fisch for the Archives of American Art's Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America in Renk's home and studio in San Francisco, California.
Women artists; Drawings; Painters -- California -- San Francisco; Jewelers -- California -- San Francisco; Women jewelers; Video recordings; Metal-workers -- California -- San Francisco; Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America; Merritt, Francis Sumner, 1913-2000; Slivka, Rose; Smith, Paul J., 1931-; Soldner, Paul
- Merry Renk Papers, 1952-2000; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 3
  Scope and Contents
  Series comprises business records that include sales invoices, inventories, exhibition price lists, and correspondence with Greta Daniel, Mrs. Vanderbilt Webb, Conrad Brown, Rose Slivka, Paul Soldner, Paul J. Smith, Alice W. Nichols, Roger Armstrong, and Francis S. Merritt. Also found is other material related to Renk's business activities; printed materials including clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and miscellaneous items; a few sketches of utensils; writings including an unpublished typescript with illustrations titled "Memories for My Children's Children's Children's Children's Children's Children" and a draft of Renk's biographical statement; and a video recording containing the documentary "Merry Renk: Jeweler" by Alan Leveton.
  - Business Records, 1953-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1954-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Included are clippings from the magazines Craft Horizons, American Craft, Ceramic Age, and other craft publications.
  - Documentary, "Merry Renk: Jeweler", circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1952-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1952-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, 1971-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Folder contains a program for The Arts Commission of San Francisco award ceremony, a press release by the Smithsonian Institution, and a travel schedule for the exhibition Messengers of Modernism: American Studio Jewelry, 1940-1960.
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
    Folder contains the book Pay Dirt!: San Francisco, The Romance of a Great City.
  - Sketches of Utensils, circa 1960-circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings, Draft of Biographical Statement, circa 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Writings, Unpublished Typescript - "Memories for My Children's Children's Children's Children's Children's Children", 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)